Barbara Cameron Papers, 1968-2003 GLC 63
James C. Hormel Gay & Lesbian Center, San Francisco Public Library
Barbara Cameron Papers,
1968-2003
GLC 63
Cameron, Barbara M., 1954-2002
2.0 cartons + 5 oversized folders (2.0 cubic feet)
James C. Hormel Gay & Lesbian Center, San Francisco Public Library 100 Larkin Street San Francisco, CA, 94102 (415) 557-4400 info@sfpl.org
Barbara M. Cameron was a Native American lesbian writer, speaker, photographer, and political activist. Her papers include speeches, writings, subject files, photographs, audiotapes, and printed materials on the subjects of: rights for lesbians, for women and for Native Americans; race; HIV education; and homophobia.
Access
The collection is available for use during San Francisco History Center hours, with photographs available during Photo Desk hours.
Accession note
Donated by Rhys Boyd-Farrell, July 10, 2006.
Materials Discarded
The following newspaper sections about the deaths of Harvey Milk and George Moscone have been discarded as they duplicate holdings in the San Francisco History Center's collection: San Francisco Chronicle, November 29, 1978 Section 1; San Francisco Examiner, November 27, 1978 Section 1; and, San Francisco Examiner, November 30, 1978 Section 1.
Biographical Note
Barbara M. Cameron was a Native American lesbian writer, speaker, photographer, and political activist. She was born on May 22, 1954 in Fort Yates, North Dakota. She was raised on the Standing Rock Sioux Reservation in South Dakota principally by her grandparents. After high school graduation, Cameron moved to Santa Fe, New Mexico where she attended the Institute of American Indian Arts. She majored in photography and film and won many awards. In 1973 she moved to San Francisco to attend the San Francisco Art Institute.
In 1975 Cameron co-founded the group Gay American Indians. She was a principal organizer of the Lesbian Gay Freedom Day Parade and Celebration (1980-1985), the executive director (1989-1992) of CUAV (Community United Against Violence), and a delegate to the 1988 Democratic Convention. She was appointed by Mayor Dianne Feinstein to the San Francisco Human Rights Commission and the Citizens Committee on Community Development, and by Mayor Frank Jordan to the Commission on the Status of Women. She also served on the Board of Directors of the San Francisco AIDS Foundation and the American Indian AIDS Institute; and she was a member of the Alice B. Toklas Lesbian/Gay Democratic Club.
In 1986 Cameron traveled to Nicaragua as a member of Somos Hermanas, a group of women who went to learn about, and show solidarity with, the women working to improve life there. She went to Berlin in 1993 to the International Conference on AIDS, participating in the International Indigenous AIDS Network. Throughout 1993 she traveled to reservations in the continental U.S. and Hawaii, working to further AIDS education.
Cameron's writing is published in several anthologies, including both versions of Our Right to Love and This Bridge Called My Back. Her writing is included in the curriculum in many colleges and universities.
Barbara Cameron died in San Francisco on February 12, 2002. She was survived by her partner of twenty-one years, Linda Boyd, and their son Rhys Boyd-Farrell.
Scope and Contents
The papers primarily document Cameron's life in San Francisco. The collection is strongest in Cameron's speeches and writings. Additional materials demonstrate her involvement with several organizations that provided support to the Native American, lesbian, and women's communities.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into six series: Series 1. Personal Papers; Series 2. Speeches and Writings; Series 3. Subject Files; Series 4. Printed Materials; Series 5. Photographs; and, Series 6. Ephemera and Audiorecordings.
Cameron, Barbara M., 1954-2002--Archives.; Chrystos, 1946- .; Indian Women--North America--Biography.; Lesbian authors--California--San Francisco--Biography.
- Personal Papers, 1971-2003; Series 1; 16.0 folders
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains correspondence, biographical information, letters of recommendation, notes on speaking engagements, sketch books, and certificates. Of particular note are the poems, letters and drawings from Menominee poet Chrystos to Cameron and Linda Boyd.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Astrological chart, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical information, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical information. Profile regarding the Women's Building, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Certificate of Honor. San Francisco Board of Superviors [in presentation cover], 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates and awards, 1983-2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    General note
    "Individual Human Rights" seminar for Golden Gate University Law School (1983); San Francisco Lesbian/Gay Freedom Day Parade and Celebration Committee (1987); Democratic National Convention delegate (1988); Alice B. Toklas Lesbian/Gay Democratic Club (1989); United Way MANAGE Program (1991); University of Oklahoma Wellness & Women IV Conference (1992).
  - Chrystos. Poems, letters and cards to Barbara Cameron and Linda Boyd, 1991-2003, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1971-2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bettina (1991)
    - Berlandt, Konstantin (1985)
    - Boyd, Linda (1994, 2002, undated)
    - Bratt, Georgia W. (1993)
    - Dunlap, Mary, CUAV donor letter (undated)
    - [Guy], Roma (1994, [1995])
    - Harper Collins (1994)
    - Hitchcock, Jodi (1991)
    - Hutton, Dorothy, R.N. (1971)
    - Levy, Chana (1983)
    - Locklear, Clisby R., North Carolina Minority AIDS Education Program (1993)
    - Melton, Bill (1994)
    - Merrill, Greg (1999)
    - Migden, Carole (2002)
    - [Norman?], Pat (1997)
    - PowWow listserve (2000)
    - Reid (1992)
    - Rink (1994)
    - Third Woman Press (2000)
    - Turney, Anthony, NAMES Project (1993)
    - Vazquez, Carmen (2001-2002)
    - Wyre, Ed (1985)
  - Human Rights Commission (San Francisco), 1988, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes letters of recommendation about Cameron written by Roma Guy, Ken Jones, and Carmen Vazquez; and a resolution passed to honor Cameron's life.
  - Obituaries, funeral mass program, memorial remembrances, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Graves, Sharol
  - Online documents found via Google searches on "Barbara Cameron,", 2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Passport, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Performance evaluation, UCSF Women's Specialty Clinic, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Resume, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sketch Books, 1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Speaking engagements (programs), 1983, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Spiral notebook [includes recipes, etc.], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Speeches and Writings, 1980-2002; Series 2
  Cameron's speeches and writings generally address issues of acceptance, racism within the lesbian and gay community, and homophobia within the Native American community. The speeches are usually shorter and include a call for action. The speech "At the Memorial for Phil Tingley" is a longer piece and muses about many subjects including HIV. Cameron's writings are often quite personal; some are diary entries, poems, and several pieces deal with friends and relatives who have died. "For Linda" is to her life partner Linda Boyd. A few of the pieces are about Cameron's trip to Nicaragua with Somos Hermanas; others are about HIV and AIDS awareness.
  Arranged into two subseries: Series 2A. Speeches; and, Series 2B. Writings. Arranged alphabetically within each subseries.
  - Speeches, 1980-1993; Series 2A; 9.0 folders
    - At the Memorial for Phil Tingley, [1991] (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bates College (speech, program correspondence), 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Family, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - [Freedom of Women], [198-] (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Gay Freedom Day Speech, June 29, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - LAVA acceptance (Bay Area Career Women), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Lesbian and Gay Freedom Day, June 1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Native Lesbians, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - "Uniting Ourselves--Bridging Our Differences" about lesbians of color, June 13, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Writings, 1981-2002; Series 2B; 36.0 folders
    - Adrian, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - As a Child I Was a Tomboy..., undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Autobiography ["Biography"], [1984] (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Be Like Mike the Lakota, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - The Body Keeps Spilling, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - The Buffalo Nation Loves Us Best, Just Ask Them: Homage to My Lakota People and the Buffalo Nation in Golden Gate Park, San Francisco, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - For Linda, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - 4 I Miss: Tommy, Marian, Marilyn, Manny, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Frybread in Berlin, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Declaration of the International Indigenous AIDS Network (June 11, 1993)
    - Henry, January 1984 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - I Wanted to Love You Johnny Grey Eyes, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Letter to Mani After His Death; Mani, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Mani Lucas
    - Letter to the Editor regarding John Carman, [1994] (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "The Life and Crimes of Gene Zuchelli: a personal gay history" (International Lesbian/Gay Freedom Day program, San Francisco, California), June 26, 1983 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Long Time, No See [screenplay?], undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Mani, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Necessary Bread Affinity Group, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Nicaragua--SOMOS HERMANAS, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Nicaragua fundraiser, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - No Apologies: A Lakota Lesbian Perspective, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - On Health and Medical Treatment, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Includes draft of "Look at me, I am not a separate woman."
    - On HIV and AIDS in Native American Communities and On Racism in Lesbian / Gay Communities, 1987-1993 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - National Native American AIDS Prevention Center survey
    - Place at the Table, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Poem drafts, 1993, 1996, undated; Contains drafts of: Mournning Becomes a Clandestine Act; The River Is Home; searching; Santa Fe 1993; When the visitors come; Nondilke; I Need to Get to Camino del Monte Sol; Wearing Short Hair in Order to be a Blonde; Look at me, I am not a separate woman; Me at Eleven; Adrian. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Poetry, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Poetry, May 1987 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Poetry, San Francisco, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Point of View, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Racism, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - "Record" [diary entries, addresses, recipes, book / movie scenes], 1994 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - "Record" [diary entries, recipes], 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - The River Is Home, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Screenplay, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - This Bridge Called My Back [program of book reading, and review of program by Linda Boyd], [1981] (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Tokenism, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
      - Agnos, Art
      - Lesbian Agenda for Action
    - Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
      Includes: Smirk Faced Goddess; Wild Turnip; Ron's (Cante ska Wicasa) Indians; The Deer of Peace, Bo Huston; "Traveling from East to West."
- Subject Files, 1968-2002; Series 3; 31.0 folders
  The series contains materials collected on such subjects as AIDS education, Nicaragua, organizations for Native Americans, Native Americans in popular culture, domestic violence, and politics. Of note is a folder of correspondence and other documents by and about Konstantin Berlandt.
  - AIDS Prevention Training, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - National Native American AIDS Prevention Center
  - Alice B. Toklas Lesbian/Gay Democratic Club, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - American Indian AIDS Institute, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - American Indian Film Festival (20th: San Francisco, California) program, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Berlandt, Konstantin (1946-1994), 1968-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
    Includes: certification of immunization; postcards and letters to Winnifred Elliott; clippings about and by Berlandt; short story "Ring My Bell;" letter from Marven Nelson dated January 27, 1991; letter from Tom Collins dated November 7, 1994; A Spring Bouquet from A Hippie Garden of Verses by Herman Berlandt (1992); resumes; "Gay Politics" by Berlandt (July 9, 1980); autobiographical sketch.
    See also:
    Box 1 / Folder 7. Correspondence (1985)
    - Berlandt, Herman
    - Collins, Tom
    - Elliott, Winnifred
    - Nelson, Marven O.
  - Braithwaite, Ron (September 29, 1960-November 13, 1994). Eulogy and funeral mass program (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Cable Car Awards program, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Clippings, 1984-1994 (Box 1, Folder 68, Oversize-folder 2)
    Includes: Wes Studi and the film Geronimo; and "Environmental Justice in Indian Country" by Gail Small (The Amicus Journal). Includes oversized folder with Women's Building interview (1984).
  - CUAV (Community United Against Violence), 1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Marks, Milton
  - Democractic National Convention, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    Includes Jesse Jackson for President '88 bumper sticker.
  - Domestic Violence, 1997-1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Incident at Oglala (Miramax Films) press kit, [1992] (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Institute on Native American Health and Wellness, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Lakol New Voices, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Lakota Books catalog, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Lakota / Dakota language course information, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Maps, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Matthews, Tede, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Nicaragua, 1987-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 79, Oversize-folder 3)
    Includes: 1987 SOMOS HERMANAS calendar with Cameron's annotations; two images of Dora Maria Tellez; Poem and card in memory of Nora Astorga (1948-1988); clipping of 9 people at a table; FSLN (Frente Sandinista de Liberacion Nacional) banner.
  - Out in Front! A Call for Leadership in Funding the Needs of Bay Area Lesbian and Gay People, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Peltier, Leonard, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - A Reception Honoring American Indian Women, May 16, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - San Francisco Bay Area Native American groups, 1991-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 83)
    Includes: "Mental Health Issues in the Context of Culture, Race and Sexuality: A Preliminary Study of Gay and Lesbian Native Americans" by Kathleen Erwin (1991); 10th Annual Silverstar program; flyers; "Save Ward Valley."
  - Sitting Bull College (Fort Yates, North Dakota), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Sovereignty for Indian Nations [cut out], undated (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Stanford Powwow (31st: Stanford, California) program, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Strawberry Press. Poetry postcards, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes: "Elegy for Chief Sealth [1786-1866]" by Duane Niatum; "Ghosts...listening to Helene sing" by Wendy Rose.
  - Two-Spirits & HIV: a Conference for the Health of Gay & Lesbian Native Americans, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Women's Building (San Francisco, California) brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Printed Materials, 1968-2002; Series 4; 18.0 folders
  The series contains published books, articles, and magazines, which generally cover lesbian or Native American subjects. Cameron's writing appears in several pieces, notably: Our Right To Love and This Bridge Called My Back.
  - Africa--The Mother of Civilization. A Multimedia Encyclopedia of Ancient Egypt (Cultural Interactive Media, Inc.), 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes: Teacher's guide; Student's guide; CD-ROM.
  - Brant, Beth (Degonwadonti). Mohawk Trail (Ithaca, New York: Firebrand Books, 1985). Food and Spirits (Vancouver: Press Gang Publishers, 1991), 1985, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Inscribed to Cameron.
  - Dillard, Annie. The Writing Life (New York: Harper and Row), 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Field, Syd. Screenplay: the Foundations of Screenwriting. 3rd edition (New York: Dell), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fields, Gary S. American Indian Music Traditions and Contributions (Portland Public Schools Geocultural Baseline Essay Series), 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - El Grito: a Journal of Contemporary Mexican-American Thought (Berkeley, California: Quinto Sol Publications), vol. 2 (1 and 4), Fall 1968, Summer 1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Kenny, Maurice. I Am The Sun: a Lakota Chant, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Kenny, Maurice. North: Poems of Home. (Chapbook no. 4, Blue Cloud Quarterly, South Dakota), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Inscribed to "Barbara and Rubin."
  - Lesbenstich 1/81. 2 Jahrgang, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Periodical in German. Includes article on Native American lesbians with photo of Cameron. Also includes letter (in English) from Jo to Cameron, February 23, 1981.
  - Native American Smoke Signals: Voice of the Nation (Mayer, Arizona), vol. 1, no. 5, August 1993 (Oversize-folder 4)
  - Official Proceedings of the 1988 Democratic National Convention (Cameron listed on p.37) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Our Right To Love: A Lesbian Resource Book (Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Pretice-Hall). Edited by Ginny Vida. Barbara Cameron piece on pp. 229-230, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - A Sampler for Social Change: Focus on Lesbian and Gay Issues" (Education Exploration Center, Minneapolis, Minnesota), Spring 1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Seven Circles Foundation Newsletter (Lagunitas, California), Spring & Summer 1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sinister Wisdom #20 (Amherst, Massachussetts), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Inscribed: "Especially for Barbara, who inspired the poem. Love Chrystos."
  - This Bridge Called My Back: Writings by Radical Women of Color (Watertown, Massachussets: Persephone Press). Edited by Cherrie Moraga, Gloria Anzaldua, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Includes piece by Barbara Cameron.
  - TJC Tribal College Journal of American Indian Higher Education, vol. 14 (no. 1), Fall 2002 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Two pieces marked: "Lakota Blood" by Danielle Rose Black Fox; and "For My Son" by Linda Jones.
  - Treaty Council News (New York and San Francisco: International Indian Treaty Council), vol. 5, no. 2, July 1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Photographs, 1977-1995; Series 5; 20.0 folders
  The series contains snapshots of Cameron and many of her friends, political events and parades. Of note are images from the Nelson Mandela rally in Oakland, some informal photographs of a women's group in Willits, California, and a photo of Cameron being sworn in that is signed by Frank Jordan.
  - Alice B. Toklas Lesbian/Gay Democratic Club paste-ups for Alice Reports, 1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Konstantin Berlandt, 1980-1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Barbara Cameron, 1981, 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    One photo of swearing in inscribed by Frank M. Jordan.
    - Frank M. Jordan
  - Barbara Cameron, Canyon Sam, San Francisco Gay Pride, June 1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Pam David, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Pam David and Carmen [Vazquez?], undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Democratic National Convention (includes negatives), 1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Roma Guy birthday, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Ken Jones (Parade Co-Chair), undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Kenny, Maurice, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - LAFA (Lesbian Agenda For Action), undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Jacqui Lewis, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Nelson Mandela rally, Oakland Coliseum, [1990] (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous: "mostly Alice [B. Toklas Democratic Club] members,", undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous: parades, Roma Guy?, photos prepared for a publication, 1995, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Diane Sabin, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Canyon Sam, 1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Somos Hermanas contingent, [Gay / Lesbian Pride] Parade, [San Francisco, California], undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - [Vazquez?], Carmen, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Willits group [some nudity], undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - [Chrystos]
    - Gearhart, Sally
    - Lichtenberg, Paula
    - Sam, Canyon
- Ephemera and Audiorecordings, 1981-1993; Series 6; 5.0 folders + 6 audiotapes
  The series contains ephemera such as a Jesse Jackson for president T-shirt from 1988, and a Greg Day for San Francisco Supervisor button. It also includes audiotapes of a few of Cameron's speaking engagements. The tapes of the readings from This Bridge Called My Back from 1981 and the Lesbians of Color panel in 1986 are probably the most significant recordings.
  Arranged into two sections: Ephemera (in alphabetical order); Audiotapes (in chronological order).
  - Award (plaque): Cable Car Award "1992 Oustanding Harvey Milk Community Service Award," (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Button: "Greg Day Supervisor,", undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Dollar Bill: "Front Line of Freedom. Lesbian/Gay Freedom Day Parade & Celebration, San Francisco. Queer as a Three Dollar Bill. [Signed by] co-chairs Barbara M. Cameron, Greg Day,", June 28, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Postcards: Hotel Santa Fe, Berlin "Gold-Else,", undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - T-shirt: "Jesse Jackson '88. 'It's Time for a change' ", 1988 (Oversize-folder 5)
  - This "Bridge" Called My Back [book reading], Friday, June 5, [1981]; 1.0 audiotape (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Formando Un Puente...Building Bridges (Oakland, California: Redwood Records), 1984; 1.0 audiotape (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Lesbians of Color (Cameron, Harris, Ordona, Vazquez), [June 21, 1986]; 1.0 audiotape (Box 2, Folder 46)
    A presentation on Cross-Racial Hostility by Barbara Cameron, Virginia Harris, Trinity Ordona and Carmen Vazquez. Part of "Coming Out And Surviving: A Conference for/by Lesbians of Color." The first Bay Area Lesbians of Color Conference was held June 21, 1986 at the Women's Building in San Francisco.
  - Counting Crows: "August & Everything After"; Gipsy Kings: "Mosaique,", [1989, 1993]; 1.0 audiotape (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - OUT93--1993 Outwrite Writer's Conference. Public Conversation: Chrystos, Cheryl Clarke, 1.0 audiotape (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Indian Voice 16 min. long (side A); Marian's Visit B-Day (side B), undated; 1.0 audiotape (Box 2, Folder 47)